THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、組織名均為虛構）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（與任何特定事件或現象無關）
I heard that the palace woman who drowned and died killed herself,
聽說那個溺死的宮女是自殺的
she was the maid for the Garnet Pavilion.
好像是柘榴宮的婢女
She was the one
據說在園遊會
who poisoned Lady Lishu at the garden party.
對里樹娘娘下毒的人就是她
Maybe she did it for her master, Concubine Ah-Duo.
我想她可能是為了 主子阿多妃才這麼做的吧
The Pure Concubine?
淑妃阿多妃嗎？
Yes.
對
It was rumored that she'd be removed
有謠言說她四夫人之一的地位
from the four ladies and replaced by a younger concubine.
將會由一位更年輕的嬪妃取代
Concubine Ah-Duo, at age 35, is a year older than the Emperor.
阿多妃三十五歲，比皇帝年長一歲
She lost a boy that she had when the Emperor was still
在皇帝還是東宮時
the Eastern Palace.
兩人間曾有一個夭折的孩子
The rear palace exists to have as many children as possible. It can't be helped…
後宮的制度就是為了盡可能地 生下更多皇子，雖然是無可奈何…
A mother of a dead baby boy, huh?
失去過兒子的母親啊…
If Lady Lihua continues to not have children, will she have the same fate?
如果梨花娘娘一直懷不了孩子 是不是也會有同樣下場呢？
Same with Lady Gyokuyou.
玉葉娘娘也是
You never know for how long she will be the Emperor's favorite.
誰都無法斷言 皇帝會寵愛她到什麼時候
Even beautiful flowers will wilt one day.
再美的花，終有一天也會枯萎
Flowers of the rear palace must bear fruit to have value.
後宮的花朵若結不出果實就毫無意義
I have to go back soon.
我差不多該回去了
Take this, too.
這個也拿著吧
It's leftovers from the tea party yesterday.
這是昨天茶會剩下的點心
Thank you!
謝謝
You have so many snacks that you have leftovers?
竟然還剩這麼多點心
Tea parties are amazing!
茶會真的好棒喔
You think?
是嗎？
Tea parties are duties that concubines must fulfill.
茶會是嬪妃之間重要的工作
Maomao, you get ready, too!
貓貓，妳也快去準備好
There's another one?
又是茶會嗎？
Everyone seems to be especially energized.
今天大家感覺都特別有精神呢
Of course we are.
當然囉
The Virtuous Concubine, Lady Lishu, is coming!
因為來的可是上級妃子 德妃里樹娘娘呢
The microcosm of the rear palace can be found in this one room.
即將在這裡上演的 簡直就是後宮的縮影
Welcome, Concubine Lishu.
歡迎妳來，里樹妃
Thank you.
謝謝
Poking at each other's hidden motives.
也就是妃子之間的互相刺探
Is it the fate of all women to be on edge
遇上同性時會開始警戒的
when facing other women?
也就只有女人這種生物了吧？
Honestly,
老實說
it's more tense than when the Emperor comes to visit.
皇帝來訪時，都還沒如此緊繃
Lady Gyokuyou is gathering information even in a friendly conversation.
在噓寒問暖中 也能打探出消息的玉葉娘娘
She may look gentle, but she's still a concubine.
看似溫柔和順，但仍有妃子風範
She apparently sends the information she collects back home.
她似乎會將收集到的消息傳回家鄉
Her home is a resting point for trade,
由於那是一個貿易中繼點
so it must be important to understand
所以掌握人潮和時勢的流轉
the flow of people and the times.
勢必非常重要吧
The food taster at the garden party?
園遊會時的試毒人？
I'm glad she hadn't been punished that harshly.
看來沒有受到嚴厲的懲罰，太好了
I won't bite, you know.
我又不會咬人
The other attendants aren't paying attention to their lady at all.
其他的侍女顯然沒把主子放在眼裡
But it doesn't seem that they're bullying her for now.
但現在看起來，也不像在欺負她
If my report to Sir Gaoshun was a mistake, then that's great news.
如果我給高順大人的報告弄錯了 也是一件好事吧
You don't dislike sweets, do you?
妳不討厭甜食吧？
I love sweets.
我很喜歡甜食
I'm glad.
太好了
It's cold, so I thought something like this would be nice.
因為很冷，我想試試這個或許不錯
I brewed citrus peels with honey.
用蜂蜜煮過的橘皮
It'll warm you up.
能讓身子暖起來
I hope you like it.
如果合妳胃口就好了
Oh? She can't have honey, either?
哎呀，她也不能吃蜂蜜嗎？
She's being picky again?
她又在挑嘴了
She won't even have what's offered to her?
竟然連人家招待的東西都不吃
Twitch, twitch.
抽動…
Lady Gyokuyou.
玉葉娘娘
Oh, my mistake.
哎呀
I'm sorry, Ailan.
愛藍，真對不起
It looks like we need to soak it a little longer.
看來這個要再浸泡一段時間才行
I'll offer something else.
上點別的東西吧
Can you have ginger tea?
妳可以喝薑茶嗎？
Yes, I can.
可以
Unfortunately, it looks like
真遺憾
the bullying rumors were true.
看來欺凌的事情並沒有搞錯
Oh.
噢
Leave the cleaning up to us.
打掃工作我們來就可以了
You go rest, Maomao.
妳去休息吧，貓貓
I can clean up, you know.
我明明也能打掃的啊…
How was the tea party with Concubines Gyokuyou and Lishu?
玉葉妃和里樹妃的茶會如何？
I thought it was weird to suddenly invite Lady Lishu
才正覺得有些奇怪
for a tea party.
怎麼會突然請里樹娘娘來茶會
It was his plan all along.
原來是這傢伙安排的嗎？
They seemed to enjoy themselves.
她們似乎聊得相當開心
We're not finished talking.
我話還沒說完呢
Will you let me go?
可以請您放開嗎？
About the poisoning incident at the garden party.
關於園遊會的下毒事件
Did you know that it was done by the Garnet Pavilion maid that killed herself?
犯人是那位自殺的柘榴宮婢女 妳有聽說這件事嗎？
I have heard rumors.
我聽過謠言
Do you really think she killed herself?
妳認為她真的是自殺嗎？
That's not for me to decide.
這不是我能決定的
Why would a mere maid want to
區區一名婢女
put poison on Lady Lishu the Virtuous Concubine's plate?
有什麼理由在 德妃里樹妃的食物下毒？
I have no idea.
我不知道
Then, could you go help at the Garnet Pavilion starting tomorrow?
那麼，從明天開始 妳能去柘榴宮幫忙嗎？
"Could you?"
“能去嗎？”
He says that, as if I have any other choice.
說得一副我能有其他選擇一樣
Yes, sir.
遵命
A pavilion's atmosphere
所謂的宮殿
is determined by its master.
往往會染上其主人的風格
Lady Gyokuyou's Jade Pavilion is homey, and Lady Lihua's
玉葉妃的翡翠宮和樂融融
Crystal Pavilion was
梨花妃的水晶宮
noble and refined.
則是高貴雅緻
And the Garnet Pavilion where Lady Ah-Duo lives is
而阿多妃居住的柘榴宮
efficient, elegant, and practical.
沒有過度裝飾，高雅且實際
Sorry for making you come so suddenly.
抱歉突然要妳們過來
I look forward to working with you for the next three days.
接下來三天要麻煩妳們多多幫忙了
I haven't been instructed by Sir Jinshi to do anything.
壬氏大人也沒吩咐我做任何事
Might as well work, then.
不妨就先好好工作吧
I haven't seen you around.
是生面孔呢
Who are those girls, Fengming?
風明，那些姑娘是誰？
They're here to help with the spring cleaning.
她們是來幫忙大掃除的
I see. Thank you for your work.
這樣啊，那就有勞各位了
The Pure Concubine, Lady Ah-Duo.
淑妃阿多妃
She's neither flashy nor plump,
雖然打扮並不華麗，身材也不豐滿
but she's both feminine, masculine, and dignified. She's beautiful.
但也因此彰顯了 那份中性的凜然與美感
So she's 35, huh?
這樣子竟然是三十五歲嗎？
If she wore the robe, one could mistake her for a young civil servant.
如果換上官服 可能還會被錯當成年輕的文官
She might look better in hufu,
比起嬪妃慣穿的大袖衫和衣裙
rather than the robe and skirt for concubines.
她穿胡服或許會更好看
Looks like they're into her.
是崇拜的眼神
She reminds me of someone.
總覺得很像誰呢
Ms. Fengming, the head lady-in-waiting.
侍女長風明
She must come from a good family based on her position,
既然當上淑妃的侍女長 想必也是出身不俗的千金
but she's very friendly.
但態度非常親和
First, can you hang these books out to dry?
首先，可以拜託妳們幫忙曬書嗎？
If anything is too heavy, just give it to a eunuch.
重物拜託其他宦官處理就行了
As expected of a veteran high-ranking concubine.
不愧是在後宮待上多年的上級妃子
Though the mansion is clean,
雖然宮殿非常整潔
it's packed with things.
但東西堆得不少
Similar to the Jade Pavilion,
與翡翠宮類似
the Garnet Pavilion attendants are hard workers.
柘榴宮的侍女也都很賣力工作
I'd like to show this to the ladies who are all talk, no work.
真想讓那些光出張嘴的侍女們 看看這等光景
We're finished here.
這樣就結束了
You already got this much done?
好厲害，妳已經做了這麼多了？
And everything is so neat. You're a big help.
而且還排得井然有序，真是幫大忙了
Can you help at the reception room, too?
也可以麻煩妳去前廳幫忙嗎？
Yes, ma'am.
是
She's friendly, observant, and praises others well.
不僅友善、擅長觀察 也很會稱讚別人
She's skilled in employing others as the head lady-in-waiting.
身為侍女長，她很懂得用人之道
I haven't done physical labor in a while. I'm tired.
好一陣子沒做勞力活了，好累
-Good work. Thank you for helping today. -Not at all.
-辛苦了，謝謝妳今天的幫忙 -不客氣
You're spending the night at the Garnet Pavilion, right?
對了，妳今晚會住在柘榴宮吧？
Come with me.
跟我來一下吧
A sweet scent?
甜香？
Use this. It'll be cold tonight.
不嫌棄的話用這個吧，今晚會很冷
Thank you, ma'am.
謝謝
Rest well.
好好休息
I haven't been told by Sir Jinshi to do anything,
壬氏大人沒有給我任何吩咐
but…
但是…
Would I really find the mastermind behind the poisoning here?
這裡真的有下毒事件的幕後黑手嗎？
Everyone truly works hard.
大家果然都很勤快
Not just the attendants, but…
而且不只是侍女…
Ms. Fengming!
風明大人！
We can do the wiping down there.
這種工作我們來做就可以了
It's all right, it's nothing.
沒關係啦，這沒有什麼
I just noticed it, that's all.
我只是剛好看到罷了
Ms. Fengming is the leader of the pack.
眾侍女都以風明侍女長為首
She's past the age to get married,
雖然已經過了適婚年齡
but if she had, she would've been a good wife.
但如果嫁人的話，一定會是個賢妻吧
Did she not consider getting married?
她沒有過結婚的念頭嗎？
Maybe she chose to dedicate her whole life to Concubine Ah-Duo.
還是說，她選擇了 一輩子服侍阿多妃呢？
A strong sense of loyalty
強烈的忠誠心
could very well be the motive for the poisoning.
也有可能構成下毒殺人的理由
Now that a new concubine may be coming,
在有新的嬪妃可能入宮的現況下
Lady Ah-Duo's position is at the
最有可能失去上級妃子地位的
highest risk.
就是阿多妃
But what if another seat opens up before that?
但要是在那之前 先空了位置出來呢？
The Emperor only reacts positively to ripened fruits.
皇帝只喜歡成熟豐滿的果實
As such, he does not visit Lady Lishu.
因此並未臨幸過里樹娘娘
This is great news, considering her age of 14,
考量到她只有十四歲的話 這應該是件好事
but she's also not fulfilling her duties as a concubine.
但也不得不說 這樣並沒有盡到身為妃子的職責
If the poison attempt was done for Concubine Ah-Duo,
如果是為了維護阿多娘娘而下毒
Lady Lishu is a reasonable target.
那麼對里樹娘娘下手，也並不奇怪
Can someone help here?
有人可以來幫忙嗎？
Honey?
蜂蜜？
Ms. Fengming's home runs a bee farm.
風明大人的老家是養蜂人家
That's why you have so much high-quality honey.
難怪會有這麼多上等蜂蜜
So the sweet scent yesterday was honey.
原來昨天的甜香是蜜蠟啊
Lady Lishu?
里樹娘娘？
She's only here with the food taster?
她只帶著試毒人嗎？
Why is she at the Garnet Pavilion?
她要來柘榴宮做什麼？
Oh, right. At the tea party…
對了，在茶會上…
That's all that happened at the Garnet Pavilion.
以上就是在柘榴宮發生的事情
I see.
這樣啊
So?
然後呢？
There's nothing else for me to say.
就是如此而已，我沒有別的話可說
I don't know what he's looking for,
雖然不知道他在刺探些什麼
but I'm just a regular apothecary.
但我只是個尋常的藥師
It's not my job to be a spy.
怎麼可能做得了奸細之類的工作？
Anyways, isn't he a little too laid back these days?
話說，他最近的態度 是不是太輕佻了點？
Let me rephrase my question.
那我換個問題吧
If anyone were to use special methods to contact the outside,
如果有人能夠用特殊方法與外界聯絡
who would it be?
妳覺得會是誰？
What a mean question.
好討厭的問法
Someone who could possibly do that is
就可能性來說的話
the head lady-in-waiting, Ms. Fengming.
有可能辦到的是風明侍女長
Why do you say that?
根據是？
She had bandages wrapped around her left wrist.
她的左手腕纏著布條
The colored wood tablet from before
先前所發現上色的木簡
was wrapped around a woman's robe with burnt sleeves.
是用袖口燒焦的女子衣裳包起來的
Someone made the effort to burn different colored flames.
有人刻意製作了不同顏色的火焰
If the flames meant anything,
要說有什麼意義的話
it would be code.
應該是一種暗號
Honestly, I can't imagine
老實說
a calm head lady-in-waiting like that
我不認為像她如此穩重的侍女長
scheming anything like that, but…
會有什麼企圖，但是…
That's only my personal speculation.
那終究只是我的主觀意見
I guess you pass.
嗯，及格了
He took the chance to eat some honey.
既然能得意地吃著蜂蜜
I'm sure he knew this much.
想必他也已經調查過這些事情了
I have to give treats to good girls.
好孩子就該給點獎勵才行
-No thank you! -No need for that.
-不用了，謝謝 -不必客氣
I don't need it. Do that for someone else.
我不用了，請您送給別人吧
Just because he's good-looking, he thinks he'd get away with anything!
這傢伙真的覺得 自己長得好看就可以為所欲為
That's the kind of pervert he was!
是說，他就是這種變態啊！
Sir Gaoshun!
高順大人
I'll poison you with laxatives!
看我等等給你下瀉藥！
-You don't like sweets? -I like salt and spice.
-妳不喜歡甜食嗎？ -我喜歡吃辣
But you can eat it, right?
但妳能吃甜食，對吧？
Shit. I can't get through to him.
可惡，根本不聽人講話
If he wasn't a higher-up, I would kick him in the crotch.
要不是他位高權重 我早就給他胯下一腳了
No. I can't kick what's not there.
不行，沒有的東西踢了也是白踢
Should I just obey his orders,
要當成命令就範嗎？
or run away and keep my dignity?
還是為了保住尊嚴而逃走？
Only if this was an aconite syrup…
至少給我烏頭蜜，我還能甘願一點…
You don't dislike sweets, do you?
妳不討厭甜食吧？
I hope you like it.
如果合妳胃口就好了
Honey?
蜂蜜？
Ms. Fengming's home
風明大人的老家
-runs a bee farm. -Lady Lishu?
是養蜂人家
Syrup…
蜜…
Honey.
蜂蜜
Apothecary?
藥師？
What are you doing to my lady-in-waiting?
這是在對本宮的侍女做什麼？
Concubine Gyokuyou, this is…
玉葉妃，這是…
Whose permission do you have to do that?
是誰准你這麼做的？
Xiaomao,
小貓
he just got carried away.
大人他只是惡作劇過頭了
Will you forgive Sir Jinshi?
能請妳原諒壬氏大人嗎？
In that case, you should lick him next time, Sir Gaoshun.
那麼下次由高順大人來舔 應該沒問題吧？
Lick? Well, that's…
舔嗎？這有點…
Do you get it now?
能懂的話就好
I have a few things I need to confirm.
那麼，我有幾件想要確認的事情
Excuse us.
打擾了
Welcome… Oh?
歡迎…咦？
Sir Jinshi isn't here?
壬氏大人沒來嗎？
No. Sorry for barging in like this.
他沒來，突然來訪實在不好意思
So? What does a Jade Pavilion attendant need from me?
所以？翡翠宮的侍女 來找我有什麼事？
I need to ask you something.
有幾件事想請教您
You're from the garden party…
妳是園遊會那時的…
What is it?
妳想問什麼？
Do you dislike honey?
您不喜歡蜂蜜嗎？
How do you know?
妳怎麼知道？
It's pretty obvious.
都寫在您臉上了
Have you ever had an upset stomach from consuming honey?
您以前是否有因為蜂蜜而吃壞肚子？
It's common to dislike a certain food after
食物中毒後而不敢再吃某種食物
experiencing food poisoning.
這種事很常見
That's not what happened.
不是那樣的
I don't remember. I was just a baby.
我不記得了，我那時還是幼兒
I hear my life was at risk at one point.
聽說我的性命一度危在旦夕
My wet nurse told me never to eat it.
在那之後 奶娘就告誡我絕對不能吃蜂蜜
You're being quite rude. These are intrusive questions.
妳太失禮了吧？ 跟里樹娘娘講話如此不客氣
You didn't even protect your lady at the tea party. You're one to talk.
在茶會的時候 根本沒保護好主子的侍女還真敢說
What are those eyes?
那是什麼眼神？
You don't need to listen to an attendant like that.
您沒有必要理會那名侍女
Yes. It's rude to you, Lady Lishu, the Pure Concubine.
對啊，竟然對著 德妃里樹娘娘您如此無禮
You should kick her out!
應該趕快把她趕出去
They must make outsiders out to be the villain this way
像這樣把外人塑造成惡人，如此一來
to make her think they're her only friends.
就能讓她認為這些人是唯一的朋友
-Lady Lishu… -A sheltered rich girl like her
-里樹娘娘… -像她這種不諳世事的大小姐
would easily get tricked.
很容易就會上當
An isolated concubine
因此被孤立的妃子
must rely on her attendants.
就只能仰賴身邊的侍女
She doesn't even realize she's being bullied.
甚至沒有察覺自己被欺負了
It's a vicious cycle.
這是個惡性循環啊
I was ordered to come here. If you have
我是奉命前來的
any complaints,
如果妳們有任何怨言
say them directly to Sir Jinshi.
請直接告訴壬氏大人
To Sir Jinshi?
壬氏大人？
Directly?
直接嗎？
I should be able to get away with this much.
這點程度的騷擾應該無妨吧？
I'm excited to think how these attendants would approach that pervert eunuch.
那些侍女會用什麼理由來 接近那個變態宦官，還真是期待啊
Another question for you.
我還有另一個問題
Have you ever met Ms. Fegming,
柘榴宮的侍女長
the head lady-in-waiting at the Garnet Pavilion?
風明大人，您認識嗎？
-Xiaomao? -Sir Gaoshun,
-小貓？ -高順大人
is there a way to learn about past events in the rear palace?
有什麼方法能知道 後宮過去發生的事情嗎？
I'll look in the court archives.
我去看看宮廷的書庫吧
Thank you, sir.
謝謝
What did she find out this time?
她這次又發現了什麼嗎？
She's a clever girl.
真是個聰明的姑娘
I can't believe that she's just 17.
難以相信她才十七歲
She's knowledgeable and calm.
淵博的知識與冷靜的性情
She thinks things through rationally, and can process information well.
能夠理性地思考並處理事情的能力
She can be a bit strange, but also somewhat impressive.
雖然有些奇怪的地方 但也確實讓人佩服
Seventeen years ago,
十七年前
when the current Emperor was still the Eastern Palace,
當今的皇帝仍是東宮的時候
he had a baby boy
他和阿多妃之間
with Concubine Ah-Duo.
生下了一個男嬰
The boy has since died.
那名男嬰後來死了
The boy was born around the same time as the Emperor's brother,
同一時期出生的 還有先帝與皇太后的孩子
the child of the former Emperor and the Empress Dowager.
也就是當今皇帝的弟弟
He only had that one child as the Eastern Palace.
皇帝在東宮時期就只有那一個孩子
His only concubine was Lady Ah-Duo.
妃子也僅有阿多妃一人
The current Emperor and Lady Ah-Duo are foster siblings,
當今的皇帝與阿多妃是乳姊弟
so I get that he's attached to Lady Ah-Duo, but…
所以他對阿多妃還有些留戀 也是可以理解
I can't believe that lustful old man only had one concubine.
但那個色老頭 僅有阿多妃一名妃子，還真意外
The baby boy died 16 years ago. It was investigated by…
十六年前，男嬰死亡 負責接生的人是…
I had imagined
總覺得
that this might be the case.
我早就心裡有數
The medicinal herbs growing in the rear palace
後宮生長的大部分藥草
are ones I've been using for a long time.
是我從以前就經常使用的種類
Someone must have transported them here.
一定是某人移植過來的
A man who drags his foot like an old woman.
一個像老婦般，拖著腿行走的男人
A man so skilled in medicine that it's a waste
此人擁有在煙花巷當藥師
he's an apothecary in the pleasure district.
實在過於浪費的高超醫術
A man with one of his knee bones removed.
此人是被削去了一邊膝蓋骨的…
A former eunuch.
前宦官
LUOMEN
（羅門，流放）
What the hell are you doing?
你在搞什麼啊…
Old man?
老爹
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集預告）
Next Episode, "Reducing Two to One."
下一集，《減二為一》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻譯：歐德慧